Welcome to the last lecture of the quarter for CS231N,
CS231N 이번 학기 마지막 강의에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
and it was great to see you guys at the beginning
처음과 끝에 여러분을 뵙게 되어
and now at the end.
정말 반가웠습니다.
And this lecture is a little bit of a departure.
이번 강의는 조금 다른 방향입니다.
We're not going to teach any new materials
알고리즘 측면에서 새로운 내용을
in terms of algorithms.
가르치지는 않을 겁니다.
It's more a talk that I'd like to give to students to put
오히려 학생들에게 장기적인
a perspective both on a more longer term research
연구 발전과 오늘날 AI에서 중요한
evolution, but as well as another dimension that
또 다른 차원인 인간 관점에
is important to today's AI, which we would call it
대해 이야기하고자
the human perspective.
합니다.
So for the completeness of the material,
자료의 완전성을 위해 이 강의에서
there's a little bit of an overlap
다른 부분과 약간
that you might see from other parts of this course,
겹치는 내용이 있을 수 있지만,
but hopefully, it makes sense in a fuller way.
전체적으로 이해하는 데 도움이 되길 바랍니다.
So the title of this slide or this lecture is what we see
이 슬라이드와 강의 제목은 '우리가 보는 것과 가치 있는
and what we value, AI with the human perspective.
것, 인간 관점의 AI'입니다.
And I know that some of you have already heard about this.
이미 이 내용을 들어본 분들도 계실 겁니다.
Is really the beginning, the origin of vision,
이것은 진화와 기술 측면에서
both in terms of evolution as well as
시각의 시작, 즉 기원에
in terms of our technology.
관한 이야기입니다.
And we did talk about the first slide
우리는 동물 세계에 시각이 처음
that came to the animal world back 540 million years ago.
등장한 5억 4천만 년 전의 첫 슬라이드에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And that was when animals or trilobites, to be specific,
그때 동물, 특히 삼엽충이 광감지
developed photosensitive cells to glean
세포를 발달시켜 외부 세계를 인지하기
what the outer world is about.
시작했습니다.
And according to zoologists like Andrew Parker, what
동물학자 Andrew Parker에
happened is that because of the onset of vision,
따르면, 시각의 출현은 진화적 군비 경쟁을
it set off an evolutionary arms race, where animals
촉발했고, 동물들은 진화하거나
either evolved or died.
멸종했습니다.
And that arms race gave rise to the speciation
이 군비 경쟁은 동물의 폭발적인 종 분화를
or explosive speciation of animals,
일으켰고, 이를
which now zoologists call the Cambrian explosion
동물학자들은 캄브리아기 폭발 또는 진화의
or the big bang of evolution.
빅뱅이라 부릅니다.
And of course, you wouldn't be surprised
물론 시각은 오늘날까지도
that vision is still to this day,
많은 동물에서 주요
a primary sensory intelligent system in many, many animals.
감각 지능 시스템임을 놀라워하지 않을 겁니다.
Not all animals use vision, admittedly, but many do.
모든 동물이 시각을 사용하는 것은 아니지만, 많은 동물이 사용합니다.
And that's also one of the primary sensory systems
인간에게도 시각은 주요 감각 시스템
for humans.
중 하나입니다.
And we use vision to do everything from survival
우리는 생존, 일, 오락, 사회화, 학습,
to work to entertainment to socialization
발달 등 모든 활동에
to learning, development, and many other things.
시각을 활용합니다.
So that's the recapture or summary of evolution.
이것이 진화에 대한 요약입니다.
And we also briefly talked about computer vision being a summer
또한 1960년대 컴퓨터 비전이 몇몇 학부생을
vision project back in the 1960s as an attempt to use a couple
동원해 시각 시스템의 중요한 부분을 구성하려는
of undergrads to construct the significant portion
시도였던 여름 프로젝트였다는 점도 간략히
of the visual system.
언급했습니다.
And that was very in line with the history of AI,
이는 AI 역사와도 일치하는데, 우리는
where we tend to have clarity of the North Star,
북극성 같은 명확한 목표는 있었지만,
but underestimate how long it would take.
소요 시간을 과소평가했습니다.
We are still probably experiencing that today,
아마 지금도 그런 상황을 겪고
but a lot has happened.
있지만, 많은 발전이 있었습니다.
You don't need me to tell you that from empowering
자율주행차부터 이미지 이해, 생성
self-driving car to understanding images
AI 혁명까지, 시각이
to the generative AI revolution, we're
큰 역할을 하며 많은
seeing vision is playing a huge role, and also in many parts,
부분에서 선도하고 있다는 것은 여러분도 잘
leading the wave.
아실 겁니다.
So maybe it's time to just take a different look at this
이제 역사적 관점과 미래를 향해 이 문제를 다르게
both historically and going towards the future.
바라볼 때입니다.
Is where have we come from, and where are we going?
우리는 어디에서 왔고 어디로 가고 있나요?
And this is an important topic to discuss,
이 주제는 매우 중요합니다. 과거의
because a lot of what has happened
많은 일이 미래를
will inform what will happen.
알려주기 때문입니다.
So I'm organizing this talk in three chunks.
이 강의는 세 부분으로 구성됩니다.
Is first of all, building AI to see what humans see.
첫째, 인간이 보는 것을 AI가 보게 만드는 것.
And that's where we came from.
이것이 우리가 출발한 지점입니다.
That we were so inspired by human capability
인간의 능력에 영감을 받아
that we want to make machines that do the same.
기계도 똑같이 하길 원했습니다.
And then we'll talk about building AI
다음으로, 인간이 보지 못하는
to see what humans don't see.
것을 AI가 보게 만드는 것.
And then we'll finish with building AI to see
마지막으로, 인간이 보고 싶어 하는
what humans would like to see.
것을 AI가 보게 만드는 것입니다.
Let's start with the first one.
첫 번째 주제부터 시작하겠습니다.
Building AI to see what humans see.
인간이 보는 것을 AI가 보게 만드는 것.
Again, just a little bit of a review.
다시 한 번, 간단히 복습해 보겠습니다.
Humans are so good at seeing.
인간은 시각에 매우 능숙합니다.
We know this.
우리는 이것을 알고 있습니다.
This is a very half a century old experiment showing us
이것은 반세기 전 실험인데, 한 번도 본 적 없는
that even watching a video you've never watched
영상을 10헤르츠로 재생하면, 즉 한
played at 10 hertz, which means every frame is only about
프레임이 화면에 100밀리초 정도만
on the screen for 100 milliseconds,
나타나는데도, 인간의 눈은
you've never seen that, it's still no problem for human eyes
여전히 그 안의 목표물, 이
to detect a target, in this case, a person.
경우 사람을 감지하는 데 문제가 없습니다.
In this complex scene where you have no idea prior knowledge
이 사람이 누구인지 전혀 사전
about what this person is, it really
지식이 없는 복잡한
underscores the superb ability of human visual understanding,
장면에서도, 인간의 시각 이해 능력, 특히 객체 중심 이해
especially object-focused understanding.
능력이 뛰어남을 강조합니다.
We also have briefly mentioned that around the turn
또한 세기 전환기 즈음에
of the century, neurophysiologists
신경생리학자들이 EEG
are measuring the speed of vision in terms of humans
캡으로 측정한 뇌 전기 신호를
seeing complex objects in the form of brain signals, brain
통해 인간이 복잡한 객체를 보는 속도를 측정한
electrical signals measured from EEG caps.
것을 잠깐 언급했습니다.
And we see that differentiating or categorizing
동물과 동물을 구분하거나 분류하는 것은
animals versus animals is a very complex task,
매우 복잡한 작업이지만,
yet humans are capable of doing that at 150 millisecond
인간은 자극이 시작된 지 150밀리초 만에 이를
after the onset of the stimuli.
수행할 수 있습니다.
And this is remarkable speed given the wetware
이는 두개골 아래의 생물학적 하드웨어를
we have under our skulls.
고려할 때 놀라운 속도입니다.
Also neurophysiologists have taught us
또한 신경생리학자들은 객체
that objects is a very important functionality
인식이 인간 시각 지능에서 매우 중요한
in our visual intelligence in humans.
기능임을 알려주었습니다.
So important that there are neural correlates in our brain.
너무 중요해서 뇌에는 객체 이해에 전념하는 신경 부위들이 있습니다.
Areas that are dedicated to object understanding,
예를 들어 얼굴 영역, 장소
such as phase areas or place areas or body parts areas.
영역, 신체 부위 영역 등이 있습니다.
This shows that evolution has really spent time
이는 진화가 객체 인식과 관련된 시각
to hone in our visual intelligence skills
지능 능력을 갈고닦는 데 많은 시간을
when it comes to object recognition.
투자했다는 것을 보여줍니다.
So all this built up the history for the field of computer vision
이 모든 것이 컴퓨터 비전 분야의 역사를 쌓아왔고,
that a few decades ago, object recognition
수십 년 전부터 객체 인식이 시각
became a fundamental building block for visual intelligence.
지능의 기본 구성 요소가 되었습니다.
And we want to empower machines with that.
우리는 기계에게 그 능력을 부여하고자 합니다.
And in order to do that, we define the problem, or at least
이를 위해 문제를 정의하는데,
the original problem as given an image,
적어도 원래 문제는 이미지가
how do we empower, enable a computer to call out the objects
주어졌을 때, 컴퓨터가 이미지 내 객체가
or what the object is in the image?
무엇인지 인식하도록 하는 것입니다.
That's such an effortless task for humans.
이것은 인간에게는 매우 수월한 작업입니다.
But if you think about it, now that you've
하지만 생각해보면,
learned enough computer vision to know that mathematically,
이제 컴퓨터 비전을 충분히 배워서
there's infinite possibilities to actually recognize
수학적으로 조명, 질감, 배경, 가림, 시점,
any object because of different lighting, texture, background,
크기 조절 등 다양한 변수 때문에 어떤 객체든
occlusion, viewing angle, scaling, and whatever,
인식할 수 있는 무한한 가능성이 있다는 걸 알게
you name it.
되었죠.
So this is actually fundamentally a difficult task.
그래서 이 문제는 근본적으로 어려운 과제입니다.
The history pre-deep learning is also very interesting.
딥러닝 이전의 역사도 매우 흥미롭습니다.
There were some pretty heroic attempts
일반화 가능한 객체 인식
at solving the problem of generic generalizable object
문제를 해결하려는 꽤 용감한 시도들이
recognition.
있었습니다.
And the first wave of attempt was actually very inspired
첫 번째 시도는 사실 심리학에서 많은 영감을
by psychology itself.
받았습니다.
We self-introspect sometimes even
우리는 때때로 지나친 자기성찰까지
to the detriment of over self-introspection.
하면서 스스로를 돌아봅니다.
We think that humans compose parts.
사람들이 부품을 조합한다고 생각합니다.
We look at objects, we can see geometric parts,
우리는 객체를 볼 때 기하학적 부품을 보고,
and then we can compose them into different objects.
그것들을 조합해 다양한 객체를 만듭니다.
And that idea of using predesignated parts or shapes
미리 정해진 부품이나 형태를 특정 방식으로
and to compose them in specific ways
조합하는 아이디어가 객체 인식의
was the first wave of object recognition.
첫 번째 물결이었습니다.
So these are different work or models coming from
이것들은 70년대, 80년대, 심지어
the '70s, '80s, or even going all the way to '90s of using
90년대까지 이어진 다양한 연구나 모델로, 부품과
different parts and configurations to recognize
구성을 사용해 객체를 인식하려
objects.
했습니다.
Of course, it didn't really work.
물론, 실제로는 잘 작동하지 않았습니다.
It's mathematically beautiful and simple, but it didn't work.
수학적으로는 아름답고 단순하지만, 효과는 없었죠.
So a second wave of object recognition pre-deep learning
딥러닝 이전의 두 번째 객체 인식
was actually a really important era in the field of AI.
물결은 AI 분야에서 정말 중요한 시기였습니다.
Is really the beginning of machine learning.
바로 머신러닝의 시작이었죠.
Statistical machine learning.
통계적 머신러닝입니다.
It was the marriage between computer programming
컴퓨터 프로그래밍과 통계
and statistical modeling.
모델링의 결합이었습니다.
And with that marriage, we start to realize
그리고 그 결합으로 우리는
the world is so complex, these problems, these intelligence
세상이 매우 복잡하다는 것을 깨닫기 시작합니다.
problems, whether it's visual intelligence or language
이러한 문제들, 즉 시각 지능이든
intelligence or other kinds of intelligence,
언어 지능이든 다른 종류의
in order to generalize, we need to learn the parameters.
지능이든, 일반화하기 위해서는 파라미터를 학습해야 합니다.
It's very hard to use hand-tuned models to get good learning.
손으로 조정한 모델을 사용해서 좋은 학습을 얻는 것은 매우 어렵습니다.
We now know we need data, even though we didn't at that time
우리는 이제 데이터가 필요하다는 것을 압니다. 그 당시에는 얼마나 많은 데이터가
know how much data.
필요한지 몰랐지만요.
But we also know that we need to design or architect
하지만 우리는 또한 통계 모델을 설계하거나 아키텍처화해서
statistical models so that they have
다양한 학습 규칙을 통해 학습할 수
the capability of learning through different learning
있는 능력을 갖추어야 한다는 것도 알고
rules.
있습니다.
And because of that, we saw a blossoming of models in that era
그래서 그 시기에 랜덤 필드, 베이즈 네트워크,
where we're learning random fields or Bayes nets
서포트 벡터 머신 등 다양한
or support vector machines and all that.
모델들이 꽃피는 것을 보았습니다.
And in fact, a lot of progress was made by the time we are
사실 21세기 첫 10년 동안 객체 인식 분야에서
in the first decade of the 21st century in object recognition,
많은 진전이 있었고, 소수의 객체
that we even have international benchmarks of a small number
클래스를 대상으로 국제 벤치마크가
of object classes to encourage everybody to compare
만들어져 모두가 자신의 알고리즘을 비교하도록
their algorithms.
장려했습니다.
So we're inching together.
그래서 우리는 점점 가까워지고 있습니다.
The last unlock for object recognition, as we have learned,
객체 인식의 마지막 열쇠는 다시
again goes back to cognitive science.
인지과학으로 돌아갑니다.
So this particular psychologist, Irv Biederman,
이 심리학자 Irv Biederman은
had long conjectured that humans can recognize
인간이 엄청난 수의 객체를 인식할 수 있다고
a huge number of objects.
오래전부터 추측했습니다.
And this is intuitive for our common knowledge.
이것은 우리의 상식에 부합하는 직관적인 사실입니다.
But he actually put a number on it.
하지만 그는 실제로 숫자를 제시했습니다.
I personally call it the Biederman number,
제가 개인적으로 Biederman
which is that by age six or seven, children, he conjectured,
숫자라고 부르는 건데, 그는 6~7세 아이들이 약
were able to recognize about 30,000 to 100,000 different
3만에서 10만 개의 서로 다른 시각 범주를 인식할 수 있다고
visual categories.
추측했습니다.
And he used this-- where did he come up with?
그는 이 숫자를 어디서 얻었을까요?
This number is a combination of looking at dictionary,
이 숫자는 사전에서 명사의 수를
the number of nouns, as well as visual studies of how kids
살펴보고, 아이들이 다양한 객체를 인식하는 시각
recognize different objects.
연구를 결합한 결과입니다.
But it's a number that's pretty daunting and pretty sobering
하지만 이 숫자는 컴퓨터 비전 분야에 매우
for the field of computer vision, because up till now,
벅차고 냉정한 현실을 보여줍니다.
this is middle of the first decade of 21st century,
왜냐하면 21세기 첫 10년
we were working with tiny number of object categories and a tiny
중반까지 우리는 인간이 경험하는 것에 비해 매우 적은
number of images to work with compared to what humans
수의 객체 범주와 이미지로 작업했기
experience.
때문입니다.
And this was, as you know, the motivation
이것이 바로 ImageNet 프로젝트의
for ImageNet project, which took this number really seriously
동기였습니다. 이 프로젝트는 이 숫자를 진지하게 받아들여 심리학자
and constructed--
Biederman이
we constructed this data set that is on par with what
추측한 것과 비슷한 수준, 즉 약
the psychologist Biederman conjectured,
22,000개의 객체
which is around 22,000 object classes, over 15 million images.
클래스와 1,500만 장 이상의 이미지를 구축했습니다.
And of course, that's the beginning
물론 이것이 여러분이 이
that you start to come into this class.
수업에 들어오게 되는 시작점입니다.
Is that because of the large data provided by ImageNet,
ImageNet이 제공한 대규모 데이터 덕분에, 우리는
we start to see that powerful algorithms like neural network
강력한 알고리즘, 특히 처음에는 convolutional neural
at the beginning with convolutional neural network
network, 지금은
of course, now we use transformers and all that,
transformer 등으로 불리는
start to really show their power through big data.
알고리즘들이 빅데이터를 통해 그 힘을 발휘하는 것을 보기 시작했습니다.
And this is a generic slide for those people
이것은 이 내용을 배우지 않은 분들을 위한 일반적인
who didn't learn about this.
슬라이드입니다.
I'm going to skip this because you all know this.
여러분 모두 아시니까 이 부분은 건너뛰겠습니다.
So the quick history is, as soon as we have ImageNet,
간단한 역사로는, ImageNet이 나오고
as soon as we use convolutional neural network, a few years
convolutional neural
after the beginning of ImageNet, we
network를 사용한
saw this door blasted open in terms
지 몇 년 만에 객체 인식
of solving the problem of object recognition.
문제를 해결하는 문이 활짝 열렸습니다.
Now, we have algorithms that we can
이제 우리는 세상의
take to look at any picture in the world
어떤 사진이든 보고 크고 작고
and be able to recognize objects in the big or small
어떤 방향이든 객체를 인식할 수
and in any kind of orientation.
있는 알고리즘을 갖게 되었습니다.
Is it 100% soft?
100% 완벽한가요?
No.
아니요.
There is always a long tail problems we can solve.
항상 해결해야 할 긴 꼬리 문제들이 존재합니다.
But as far as industrial application goes,
하지만 산업적 응용 측면에서는
this has come a long way, and really has
이 문제가 크게 진전되어
been a matured problem.
성숙한 문제로 자리 잡았습니다.
And of course, all of you know, and all this
그리고 여러분 모두 아시다시피, 이 모든 것은
came at a convergence point, which is the year 2012, where
2012년이라는 수렴점에서 이루어졌습니다. 그 해 ImageNet
the ImageNet challenge provided the data
챌린지가 convolutional
for the convolutional neural network,
neural network를 위한 데이터를
and they used two GPUs at that time.
제공했고, 당시 두 개의 GPU를 사용했습니다.
And the three ingredients come together and brought
세 가지 요소가 합쳐져 딥러닝의
the moment of deep learning--
순간, 즉 딥러닝의 탄생을
the birth of deep learning.
가져왔습니다.
And in this class, we also talked a little bit
이 수업에서는 또한 지난 10년간
about different various architectures
ImageNet 챌린지가 낳은 다양한
that ImageNet challenge engendered
아키텍처, 예를 들어 convolutional
throughout the past decade or so in terms
neural network나
of convolutional neural network or ResNet and so on.
ResNet 등에 대해서도 조금 다뤘습니다.
So that's the beginning, really, about deep learning revolution.
이것이 바로 딥러닝 혁명의 시작입니다.
And of course, in terms of the quest for visual intelligence,
그리고 시각 지능을 향한 탐구는 단순히 장면
we're not going to stop at just being able to label objects
속 객체에 라벨을 붙이는 데서 멈추지 않을
in a scene.
것입니다.
For example, in this two scenes, if you just label objects,
예를 들어, 이 두 장면에서 단순히 객체만 라벨링한다면,
you'll think it's just a llama and a person.
라마와 사람이라고 생각할 겁니다.
But if I show you the second scene
하지만 두 번째 장면인 라마와
with the llama and the person, the story
사람을 보여드리면 이야기가
is completely different.
완전히 달라집니다.
Even though you have the same object,
같은 객체가 있어도
you have very different relationship.
관계는 매우 다릅니다.
So cognitive scientists, once again,
그래서 인지과학자들은 다시 한 번
was the head of computer scientist
컴퓨터 과학자들의 선두에 서서
and inspired us to think about visual intelligence
단순히 객체를 이름 붙이거나 분류하는 것을 넘어서 시각적
beyond just naming objects or categorizing objects.
지능에 대해 생각하도록 영감을 주었습니다.
In this particular paper, Jeremy Wolfe,
이 논문에서, 꽤 유명한
who is a pretty prominent psychologist,
심리학자인 Jeremy Wolfe가
wrote this beautiful paper that called out
복잡한 자연 장면을 이해하는 데
that relationships between objects
있어 객체 간의 관계가
must be coded as part of our understanding
반드시 코드화되어야 한다고 지적하는
of complex natural scenes.
훌륭한 논문을 썼습니다.
And inspired by that work, the field of computer vision
그 연구에 영감을 받아 컴퓨터 비전 분야는
started to look at how do we understand relationships.
관계를 어떻게 이해할지 연구하기 시작했습니다.
And this is early work.
이것은 초기 연구입니다.
You guys got a lecture from Ranjay last week or--
여러분은 지난주에 Ranjay의 강의를 들었죠.
yeah.
네, 지난주입니다.
This was his PhD thesis, looking at learning object relationships
이것은 그의 박사 논문으로, 장면 그래프를 표현으로 사용하여
using scene graph as a representation.
객체 간 관계를 학습하는 연구였습니다.
In this case, scene graph is defined
이 경우 장면 그래프는
by these entity nodes that are objects,
객체인 엔티티 노드들로 정의되고,
and their relationships are defined
이들의 관계는 노드 간
by the connectivity between the nodes,
연결성으로 정의되며,
or sometimes they have attribute relationships that
때로는 특정 객체를 정의하는
defines the particular objects.
속성 관계도 포함됩니다.
And even a thing as simple as this
그리고 이렇게 단순하게 두 사람이
with mostly just two people, one feeding a cake to the other,
한 사람이 다른 사람에게 케이크를 먹이는 장면만 있어도,
you can form a very dense scene graph because of the richness
시각 장면의 풍부함 때문에 매우 밀집된 장면 그래프를
of the visual scene.
만들 수 있습니다.
And this was Ranjay's thesis after the object recognition
이것은 객체 인식 오류 이후 Ranjay의 논문으로, 우리는
error, where we build a data set called visual genome, where
visual genome이라는 데이터셋을 구축했는데,
we try to put together object relationships, also
여기서는 객체 관계와 이야기 설명을 함께 모으려고
story descriptions.
했습니다.
And one of the work that Ranjay did
Ranjay가 한 작업 중 제가
I thought that was really fun was zero shot learning
정말 재미있다고 생각한 것은 특이한
of unusual object relationships.
객체 관계의 제로샷 학습이었습니다.
For example, it's not unusual to see person riding a horse.
예를 들어, 사람이 말을 타는 것은 흔한 일이죠.
It's not unusual to see person wearing a hat,
사람이 모자를 쓰는 것도 흔한 일이지만,
but it's unusual in general, to see horse wearing hat.
말이 모자를 쓰는 것은 일반적으로 드문 일입니다.
And in the era of big data training,
빅데이터 학습 시대에도 이런 종류의 데이터를
it's hard to get this kind of data
반복해서 얻기 어렵습니다.
repeatedly because you just don't have too many of that.
왜냐하면 그런 데이터가 많지 않기 때문입니다.
But using this compositional scene graph representation,
하지만 이 합성 장면 그래프 표현을 사용하면
we're able to learn the more common relationships, and then
더 흔한 관계들을 학습하고, 그
derive uncommon relationships in that representation.
표현에서 드문 관계들도 유도할 수 있습니다.
And again, this is another example
그리고 다시 말하지만, 이것은
of zero shot learning, where person sitting on chair and fire
제로샷 학습의 또 다른 예로, 의자에 앉은 사람이나
hydrant on the lawn or on the field
잔디밭이나 들판에 있는
are all common relationships, but person
소화전은 모두 흔한 관계지만,
sitting on fire hydrant is the one that would not--
소화전에 앉은 사람은 데이터가 부족해서 얻기
it's hard to get data.
어려운 관계입니다.
And we're able to do that to make that happen.
우리는 그것을 가능하게 만들 수 있었습니다.
And this is just a figure from the paper that shows that
이것은 논문에서 가져온 그림으로,
Ranjay's work at that time achieved state-of-the-art
당시 Ranjay의 연구가 다른 많은 방법들과
recognition rate compared to many other methods.
비교해 최첨단 인식률을 달성했음을 보여줍니다.
But relationship is not enough.
하지만 관계만으로는 충분하지 않습니다.
The ability to actually tell a story that
더 풍부한 이야기를 실제로
is a lot more richer, or also using natural language
전달하는 능력, 즉 자연어를
is actually the next big goal.
사용하는 것이 다음 큰 목표입니다.
So around the year 2014--
그래서 2014년경, 그 문제에 대해 연구를
around 2014, we start working on that problem and think about it.
시작하고 고민하기 시작했습니다.
That's just two years after the image that Alex, that moment.
그것은 Alex의 이미지가 나온 지 불과 2년 후였습니다.
But the field was starting to evolve so fast.
하지만 이 분야는 매우 빠르게 발전하고 있었습니다.
We're so inspired by what we can do
우리는 합성곱 신경망과 LSTM이라는
using a combination of convolutional neural network
언어 모델의 조합으로 할 수
as well as a language model called LSTM.
있는 일에 매우 영감을 받았습니다.
And this is the thesis by Andrej Karpathy
이것은 Andrej Karpathy의
that we were one of the first teams that
논문으로, 우리가 이미지 캡셔닝이나 스토리텔링, 그리고
showed how to do image captioning or storytelling, as
Justin Johnson이 수행한 작업의 일부인 밀집
well as dense captioning, which is also part of the work
캡셔닝을 어떻게 하는지 처음으로 보여준 팀
that Justin Johnson did.
중 하나였습니다.
And I know he's one of the co-instructors of this course.
그리고 그는 이 강좌의 공동 강사 중 한 명임을 알고 있습니다.
And that was around the time between 2015 to 2018.
그것은 2015년부터 2018년 사이의 시기였습니다.
A lot of work has happened to solve the problem.
이 문제를 해결하기 위해 많은 연구가 진행되었습니다.
Of course today, using a multimodal LLMs,
물론 오늘날에는 멀티모달 LLM을
we have taken the solution of this problem
사용해 이 문제 해결을
even to another notch.
한 단계 더 발전시켰습니다.
But this is the beginning of that line of work.
하지만 이것이 그 연구 분야의 시작입니다.
And frankly, I myself, as a computer vision scientist
솔직히 말해서, 저 자신도 세기 초에 이 분야에
who entered the field at the beginning of the century,
들어온 컴퓨터 비전 과학자로서,
was very surprised by how fast our field was able to solve
데이터와 신경망 알고리즘만 확보되자마자 우리
this problem, as soon as we've got data, as well
분야가 이 문제를 얼마나 빠르게
as neural network algorithms.
해결했는지 매우 놀랐습니다.
But a much harder problem is actually in dynamic scenes.
하지만 훨씬 더 어려운 문제는 사실 동적 장면에 있습니다.
In dynamic scenes, we tend to have much more
동적 장면에서는 훨씬 더 복잡한 관계가
complex relationships.
존재합니다.
Much more complex movements.
훨씬 더 복잡한 움직임들이 있죠.
And also the camera movement or the entity,
그리고 카메라 움직임이나 장면 내의 객체, 즉 배우들이
the actors within the scene can do a lot of different things.
다양한 행동을 할 수 있습니다.
So in this work that a collaboration with Esan
그래서 Esan과 우리 연구실
and a bunch of students in our lab,
학생들과의 협업으로 진행한 이 연구에서는
we call it multi-object multi-actor activity
이를 다중 객체 다중 배우 활동 이해라고
understanding.
부릅니다.
This is a much newer work.
이 연구는 훨씬 더 최근의 작업입니다.
We only published this a couple of years ago.
우리는 이 연구를 불과 몇 년 전에 발표했습니다.
To capture the relationship between these actors
동적 장면에서 이 배우들과 그들의 활동 간의 관계를
and their activities in dynamic scene is still,
포착하는 문제는 아직도, 제가 말하건대,
I would say, an unsolved problem.
해결되지 않은 문제입니다.
And this will have profound implications.
이 문제는 매우 깊은 영향을 미칠 것입니다.
You know that you're in Silicon Valley.
여러분은 실리콘밸리에 있으니 아시겠지만,
So you're hearing so much excitement of robots,
예를 들어 로봇에 대한 엄청난 기대감을 많이 듣고 계실
for example.
겁니다.
If we ever dream to have everyday robots that
만약 우리가 일상에서 함께 일하는 로봇을
work amongst us, robots need to solve this problem.
꿈꾼다면, 로봇은 이 문제를 해결해야 합니다.
Understand how complex the scene is, what people are doing,
장면이 얼마나 복잡한지, 사람들이 무엇을 하는지, 누가 무엇을 하는지,
who is doing what, what is next.
다음에 무엇이 일어날지 이해해야 하죠.
And this is an unsolved problem.
이것은 아직 해결되지 않은 문제입니다.
Also in addition to what I have shown you,
또한 제가 보여드린 것 외에도, 여러분은
you have learned a little bit in this class and related computer
이 수업과 관련된 컴퓨터 비전 문제에 대해 조금
vision problem, but we didn't have time to elaborate.
배웠지만, 자세히 다룰 시간이 없었습니다.
For example, 3D computer vision or human pose understanding.
예를 들어 3D 컴퓨터 비전이나 인간 자세 이해 같은 것들이죠.
And of course, generative AI and generative models.
그리고 물론 생성 AI와 생성 모델도 있습니다.
So this is just to show you that the field
이것은 현대 AI가 부활한
of computer vision since the rebirth of modern AI
이후 컴퓨터 비전 분야가 얼마나 엄청나게
has been just moving extraordinarily fast.
빠르게 발전해 왔는지를 보여주기 위한 것입니다.
But the take home message in this section for me
하지만 이 섹션에서 제가 전달하고 싶은
is that two things.
핵심 메시지는 두 가지입니다.
One is that data, compute and neural network algorithm truly
첫째는 데이터, 연산 능력, 신경망 알고리즘이 약 10년
have converged about 10 years ago or 13 years ago.
전 또는 13년 전에 진정으로 융합되었다는 점입니다.
And that was the moment that modern AI or deep learning
그때가 현대 AI 또는 딥러닝 혁명이 일어난
revolution has happened.
순간이었습니다.
But the history of that, and so much
하지만 그 역사와 우리가
of the problem that we have been working on,
작업해 온 많은 문제들은
is truly inspired by cognitive science and psychology
인지과학, 심리학, 신경과학에서 진정한 영감을
and neuroscience.
받았습니다.
And that, to me, is going to continue to happen.
그리고 저에게 그것은 앞으로도 계속될 것입니다.
Is that we will continue to be inspired by what the brain can
즉, 우리는 뇌가 할 수 있는 것과 뇌가 일을 처리하는
do or how the brain does things, and also
방식을 계속해서 영감을 받을 것이고, AI를
will continue to use AI to help our brain research.
사용해 뇌 연구를 돕는 일도 계속할 것입니다.
So there is a very intimate relationship between today's AI
그래서 오늘날 AI와 인지과학, 신경과학,
and cognitive science, neuroscience, brain science,
뇌과학 사이에는 매우 밀접한 관계가
and all that.
있습니다.
So that's the first section.
이것이 첫 번째 섹션입니다.
And of course, a lot of people, students and collaborators
그리고 물론 제가 방금 발표한 내용에는
have contributed to what I have just presented.
많은 학생들과 협력자들이 기여했습니다.
Now, let's talk about going beyond just building
이제 인간이 보지 못하는 것을 보기 위해 AI를 단순히 구축하는
AI to see what humans don't see.
것을 넘어서는 이야기를 해보겠습니다.
This is where pushing AI beyond the capability of humans or you
이것이 바로 AI를 인간 능력 이상으로, 즉 초인적으로
can call it super humans.
발전시키는 부분입니다.
For example, most people don't recognize a ton of dinosaurs.
예를 들어 대부분 사람들은 공룡을 많이 인식하지 못합니다.
You can probably name a few.
아마 몇 가지 이름만 대실 수 있을 겁니다.
Some kids really can name a lot.
어떤 아이들은 정말 많은 이름을 알 수 있습니다.
Well, let alone thousands and tens
수천, 수만 종의 새
of thousands of bird species or tens of thousands
종류나 수만 개의 자동차 종류는
of car categories.
말할 것도 없고요.
So this is the line of work that I call fine-grained object
이런 일을 저는 세밀한 객체 분류(fine-grained object categorization)라고
categorization.
부릅니다.
Humans are just not that good at it.
인간은 이걸 그렇게 잘하지 못합니다.
And this is still a problem that I
솔직히 말해서, 이 문제는 아직 완전히
don't think we're fully solved yet, to be honest.
해결되지 않았다고 생각합니다.
In this generative AI era, especially, we're
특히 이 생성 AI 시대에, 우리는
talking a lot about multimodal LLMs.
멀티모달 LLM에 대해 많이 이야기하고 있죠.
This problem has somewhat been neglected,
이 문제는 다소 간과되었거나
or it just is not a mainstream problem.
주류 문제는 아닙니다.
But it really will--
하지만 여전히
still will come and play an important role.
중요한 역할을 할 겁니다.
So in this early work of fine-grained bird species
이 초기 세밀한 새 종
recognition, we put together, a data set--
인식 연구에서, 우리는 4,000마리
actually, we used a data set of 4,000 birds.
새 데이터셋을 모았습니다.
And as you can see, as we go down
보시다시피,
the tree of the species, the errors, actually,
종 분류 단계가 올라갈수록, 즉 더 일반적인
as we go up the species, as we have more general names,
이름일수록 오류가 줄어듭니다. 다시
the error decreases, which means it's a convoluted way of saying,
말해, 세밀한 수준에서
by the time you're reading the fine-grained level,
여전히 많은 오류가 발생한다는
we still make a lot of errors.
뜻입니다.
The algorithm are still not totally ready.
알고리즘이 아직 완전히 준비되지 않았습니다.
Another work that I find fascinating
제가 흥미롭게 생각하는
is that a few years ago, a group of students in my lab
또 다른 연구는 몇 년 전 제 연구실 학생들이 만든 세밀한
trained a fine-grained car classifier
자동차 분류기입니다.
in terms of make, model, and year.
제조사, 모델, 연도별로 분류했죠.
It turns out after 1970s, there are thousands of car models that
1970년대 이후로는 제조사, 모델, 연도별로 수천
are defined by different make, model, and year.
개의 자동차 모델이 존재합니다.
And then you can take--
우리는 미국 전역
we took Google Street View images from 200 or 100, I think,
100~200개 주요 도시의 Google Street View
major cities across the country.
이미지를 사용했습니다.
And then we use the fine-grained car detectors
그리고 세밀한 자동차 탐지기를 이용해
to detect what are the cars on the street of these cities.
이 도시 거리의 자동차를 탐지했습니다.
And we use it as a lens to study social patterns.
이걸 사회 패턴을 연구하는 렌즈로 사용했죠.
For example, what is the pattern here,
예를 들어, 제가 보여준
I showed education patterns.
교육 패턴입니다.
Car models and education patterns
자동차 모델과 교육
are highly correlated or income patterns, highly correlated.
수준, 소득 패턴이 매우 높은 상관관계를 보였습니다.
In that paper, we show voting
그 논문에서는 투표 패턴도 매우 높은 상관관계를 보였고,
Or even environmental patterns, highly correlated.
환경 패턴도 마찬가지였습니다.
So it's a really interesting way of using computer vision
그래서 컴퓨터 비전을 사회를 연구하는 렌즈로
as a lens to study our society.
활용하는 매우 흥미로운 방법입니다.
And no human, no individual human,
어떤 인간도, 심지어
not even a collection of humans can do this easily at all.
인간 집단도 이걸 쉽게 할 수 없습니다.
So AI is really pushing the boundary of what humans can see.
그래서 AI는 인간이 볼 수 있는 한계를 확장하고 있습니다.
To drive home this idea, let's do a couple of tests.
이 아이디어를 확실히 하기 위해, 몇 가지 테스트를 해보겠습니다.
Humans actually have our limitations.
인간도 한계가 있습니다.
I just talked about celebrating human's ability of seeing.
방금 인간의 시각 능력을 칭찬했지만,
But we also have our limitations.
우리는 한계도 가지고 있습니다.
This is a very famous visual illusion
이것은 매우 유명한 시각 착시 테스트인
test called Stroop test.
Stroop 테스트입니다.
And the idea is that you all can read the words.
여러분은 단어를 읽을 수 있습니다.
But if I ask you to read the color of the word as fast
하지만 단어의 색깔을 가능한 빨리 왼쪽에서 오른쪽,
as possible, going from left to right and top to down,
위에서 아래로 읽으라고 하면 쉽지
you find that it's not that easy.
않다는 걸 알게 됩니다.
Try to read it, like red, yellow, green, purple, blue,
읽어보세요, 빨강, 노랑, 초록, 보라, 파랑,
black, orange.
검정, 주황.
It's fighting with you.
이게 여러분과 싸우는 거죠.
This is the fight between visual attention and all that.
이것은 시각적 주의력과 그 모든 것 사이의 싸움입니다.
Here's another example.
여기 또 다른 예가 있습니다.
There are two alternating images of the picture.
그림이 두 개의 교차하는 이미지로 되어 있습니다.
And there's one change.
그리고 한 가지 변화가 있습니다.
A pretty big change that's happening between the two
두 교차하는 그림 사이에 일어나는 꽤
alternating pictures.
큰 변화입니다.
I don't know if you spot the change.
변화를 발견하셨는지 모르겠습니다.
Do you spot it?
발견하셨나요?
The enine--
엔진--
Yes, it's the engine.
네, 엔진입니다.
So it takes a while to spot it.
그래서 발견하는 데 시간이 좀 걸립니다.
So this is a very famous psychology experiment
이것은 변화맹(change blindness)이라는 아주 유명한
called change blindness.
심리학 실험입니다.
Now, all this is fun.
이 모든 것이 재미있습니다.
Stroop test is fun, this is fun.
스트룹 테스트도 재미있고, 이것도 재미있습니다.
But this is not fun.
하지만 이것은 재미없습니다.
That human attention is limited.
인간의 주의력은 한계가 있습니다.
And in some situations in our working life,
그리고 어떤 상황에서는 우리의 업무 생활에서
that kind of attention limit can be dire.
그런 주의력 한계가 치명적일 수 있습니다.
For example, medical errors are the third leading cause
예를 들어, 의료 과실은 미국 의료 시스템에서
of death in America's health care system.
세 번째로 큰 사망 원인입니다.
And of course, leaving this pair of scissors
물론, 환자의 몸 안에 가위를
in the body of the patient is the iconic image
남겨두는 것은 의료 과실의 상징적인
of medical errors.
이미지입니다.
But there are so many medical errors.
하지만 의료 과실은 매우 많습니다.
Pharmaceutical errors, there's procedure errors,
약물 오류, 절차 오류, 사무 오류,
clerical errors, diagnostic errors.
진단 오류 등이 있습니다.
So one has to be very careful.
그래서 매우 조심해야 합니다.
For example, in surgery rooms, honestly, scissors
예를 들어, 수술실에서는 솔직히 가위가 몸 안에
don't get left in the bodies, typically, but much smaller
남는 경우는 보통 없지만, 훨씬 작은 것들, 예를
things like suture, needles, or piece of gauze and all that.
들어 봉합 바늘이나 거즈 조각 같은 것들이 남을 수 있습니다.
So today, most of this is still just tracked by hands.
그래서 오늘날 대부분은 여전히 손으로 추적하고 있습니다.
We have these checklists to track in the surgery rooms.
수술실에서는 이런 것을 추적하기 위한 체크리스트가 있습니다.
If something is missing, the surgery has to be paused.
무언가 빠지면 수술을 일시 중지해야 합니다.
On average, that pause is close to an hour.
평균적으로 그 일시 중지는 거의 한 시간에 가깝습니다.
And think about the danger for the patient.
그리고 환자에게 얼마나 위험한지 생각해 보십시오.
The exposure to bacteria and the bleeding
그 항목을 찾기 위해 박테리아
and all that, just because we have to search for that item.
노출과 출혈 등이 발생할 수 있습니다.
So if there is a way to use AI to help our doctors,
그래서 AI를 사용해 의사와 외과의를 도와 항목을 추적할 수
surgeons, to track items, that would be so powerful.
있다면 매우 강력할 것입니다.
And this is just a demo.
이것은 단지 데모입니다.
This is not a deploy system.
배포 시스템이 아닙니다.
We're not there in terms of fidelity.
정확도 면에서는 아직 그 단계에 이르지 못했습니다.
But this is a demo to show that we
하지만 이것은 AI를 사용해
can use AI to count, in this case, gauze and all that.
이 경우 거즈 등을 세는 것이 가능하다는 것을 보여주는 데모입니다.
And this is just an example of pushing AI
이것은 AI가 인간이 보지 못하는 것을 보도록
to see what humans don't see.
하는 예시일 뿐입니다.
Here's another example that is really fun.
여기 정말 재미있는 또 다른 예가 있습니다.
I don't know if I showed this before.
이걸 전에 보여줬는지 잘 모르겠네요.
But this is one of my favorite visual illusions,
하지만 이건 제가 가장 좋아하는 시각적 착시 중
where I'm just giving you the answer.
하나인데, 제가 답을 바로 알려드리는 겁니다.
If you look at the two squares, A and B,
체커보드 위쪽에 있는 두 사각형
on a checkerboard at the top, it is so hard
A와 B를 보면, 같은 그레이스케일이나 밝기를
to believe they have the same grayscale or luminance.
가졌다는 게 믿기 어려울 정도입니다.
And then you look at the bottom, you're like, oh.
그리고 아래쪽을 보면, 아, 그렇구나 싶죠.
Of course, they do.
물론 그렇습니다.
But why?
그런데 왜 그런 걸까요?
Even though you have the bottom picture in front of you,
아래 그림을 보고 있어도 위 그림을
seeing the top still gives you the illusion.
보면 착시 현상이 생깁니다.
Why?
왜 그럴까요?
Because evolution has pre-wired us
진화 과정에서 우리는 사물의 형태,
in conjecturing or understanding our world in its common way,
빛의 방향, 그림자가 생기는 방식 등 일반적인 물리
with the common physics of the shape
법칙에 따라 세상을
of objects, lighting source, how shadows are made, and all that,
추론하거나 이해하도록 미리 연결되어 있기 때문입니다.
this is so deep in our visual development.
이것은 우리의 시각 발달에 깊이 자리 잡고 있습니다.
That it's hard for us to see it another way.
그래서 다른 방식으로 보는 것이 어렵습니다.
So what I'm trying to get at is there's bias
제가 말하고자 하는 것은 인간의 시각 시스템에는
in our human visual system.
편향이 있다는 겁니다.
The bias might come from evolutionary construct,
그 편향은 진화적 구조에서 올 수도
the bias can come from our social experience,
있고, 사회적 경험에서 올 수도 있으며,
the data we're exposed to.
우리가 접하는 데이터에서 올 수도 있습니다.
But some of these biases can be harmful.
하지만 이러한 편향 중 일부는 해로울 수 있습니다.
When the bias happens, that became
편향이 발생하면 특정 집단에게
unfair to a group of people.
불공평해질 수 있습니다.
A community.
커뮤니티입니다.
And we have to be aware of this.
그리고 우리는 이것을 인지해야 합니다.
A few years ago, face recognition algorithm
몇 년 전만 해도 얼굴 인식
was not good, and it tends to recognize
알고리즘이 좋지 않았고, 특정 피부색이나 심지어
certain skin color and even gender better than others.
성별을 더 잘 인식하는 경향이 있었습니다.
And it has consequences.
이것은 결과를 초래합니다.
Think about self-driving car.
자율주행차를 생각해 보세요.
So think about many other medical use cases.
그리고 많은 다른 의료 사례들도 생각해 보세요.
So we have to be vigilant about this.
그래서 우리는 이에 대해 경계해야 합니다.
I do believe that AI bias has been a problem that people now
저는 AI 편향이 지금 사람들이 안고 있는 문제라고
are carrying.
믿습니다.
A few years ago, this problem was so new
몇 년 전만 해도 이 문제는 너무 새로워서
that many people are not even paying attention.
많은 사람들이 관심조차 두지 않았습니다.
But fast forward to 2025, I'm not
하지만 2025년으로 빠르게 넘어가
saying we have solved this problem,
보면, 이 문제를
but I'm personally a lot happier to see
완전히 해결했다고는 말할 수 없지만, 개인적으로
that so many people are paying attention to this,
학계뿐만 아니라 산업계에서도 이렇게
not only just in academia, but also in industry.
많은 사람들이 관심을 갖는 모습을 보니 훨씬 기쁩니다.
And then there's another kind of not seen.
그리고 또 다른 종류의 '보이지 않는 것'이 있습니다.
And this is interesting.
이것이 흥미로운 점입니다.
Sometimes not seen is exactly what
때로는 '보이지 않는 것'이 바로 우리가 원하는
we want because you want to respect privacy.
것이기도 합니다. 왜냐하면 프라이버시를 존중하고 싶기 때문입니다.
So how do you create AI that helps people to see yet
그렇다면 사람들을 돕는 AI를 어떻게
you still want it.
만들면서도,
Not to see what people don't want you to see.
사람들이 보지 않길 원하는 것은 보지 않게 할 수 있을까요?
This is a very deep--
이것은 매우 깊은 문제로,
it's a technical problem as well as a human problem.
기술적인 문제이자 인간적인 문제이기도 합니다.
So from a technical point of view,
기술적인 관점에서 보면, 머신러닝
there are many ways to consider ML, machine learning privacy.
프라이버시를 고려하는 방법은 여러 가지가 있습니다.
I'm just listing here from a visual approach point of view,
여기서는 시각적 접근 관점에서 몇 년 전에
a few years ago, our lab wrote this paper
우리 연구실에서 환자 방이나
about using smart cameras in patient rooms or patient homes
환자 집에 스마트 카메라를 사용해 의사들이 더 잘 볼 수 있도록
to help doctors to see better.
도운 논문을 소개합니다.
But even there, we have to recognize issues
하지만 그곳에서도 얼굴이나 전신
like faces or just full body information and even homes.
정보, 심지어 집 자체와 같은 문제들을 인식해야 합니다.
And this is a list of potential solutions.
이것은 가능한 해결책들의 목록입니다.
For example, you can do blurring, or you can do masking,
예를 들어, 블러 처리, 마스킹, 차원
you can do dimensionality reduction,
축소를 할 수 있고, 서버로
but you can also, try to do different approaches,
모든 데이터를 보내지 않는 연합 학습(federated
for example, federated learning so that you don't
learning)이나
send all the data to the server, or encryption and other things.
암호화 같은 다른 접근법도 시도할 수 있습니다.
So I'm not going to belabor this,
자세히 설명하지는 않겠지만, 보여드리고
but there's one work I want to show you.
싶은 연구가 하나 있습니다.
It's not even my work, but I really like this work.
제 연구는 아니지만, 정말 마음에 드는 연구입니다.
And it's a work about taking videos of people
사람들의 영상을 촬영해 행동을
and try to recognize the action of people,
인식하면서도 프라이버시를
but yet respecting the privacy of people.
존중하는 연구입니다.
How do you do that?
어떻게 하냐고요?
For example, in this case, you want
예를 들어, 이 경우에는 장면에서
to take a video of this kid moving in the scene.
움직이는 아이의 영상을 찍고 싶을 때입니다.
There are ways to do this.
이걸 할 수 있는 방법들이 있습니다.
If you blur this or defocus this or do some of these, yeah,
블러 처리하거나 초점을 흐리게 하거나 이런 방법들을 쓰면, 프라이버시는 보호할
you can provide.
수 있지만,
You can protect privacy, but you also lose enough information
동시에 이 사람이 무엇을 하는지 알 수
that you might not even know what this person is doing.
없을 정도로 정보가 손실됩니다.
And for many applications, the whole goal
많은 응용 분야에서 핵심 목표는 바로
is to know what this person is doing.
이 사람이 무엇을 하는지 아는 것입니다.
So in this particular work, led by Carl's students,
그래서 Carl 학생들이 주도한 이 연구에서는
they actually did a combination of hardware and software
하드웨어와 소프트웨어를
approach, where they had-crafted a lens that
결합한 방식을 사용했습니다. 특별히
is that actually filters visual data in a particular way.
시각 데이터를 특정 방식으로 필터링하는 렌즈를 직접 제작했죠.
So particular that if you look at the top row,
그래서 위쪽 행을 보면, 이 렌즈가 카메라에
what the lens captures into the camera
담는 영상은 프라이버시를
protects the privacy a lot.
상당히 보호합니다.
You don't see the person's face, you
사람의 얼굴도 보이지
don't see the body and so on.
않고, 몸도 보이지 않습니다.
But because it's a lens that's particularly
하지만 소프트웨어와 연동되도록
designed in connection with a piece of software,
특별히 설계된 렌즈이기
it can help to block out the movement information
때문에, 위상 정보를 유지하면서
or the human activity information
움직임 정보나 인간 활동
without backing out phase information.
정보를 차단할 수 있습니다.
So that's a really interesting approach.
정말 흥미로운 접근법입니다.
That's a hybrid between hardware and software.
하드웨어와 소프트웨어의 하이브리드인 셈이죠.
Aiming towards important applications
사람을 보호하기 위해 보고 싶지만,
that you want to see people to protect them,
프라이버시를 존중하기 위해 너무 많이 보고
but you don't want to see too much, because you
싶지 않은 중요한 응용 분야를
want to respect privacy.
목표로 합니다.
So that's a work I really like.
그래서 저는 그 연구를 정말 좋아합니다.
I really like the spirit of that work.
그 연구의 정신이 정말 마음에 듭니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
So in this part of the lecture, I shared with you
이번 강의 부분에서는 인간이 보지 못하는
a number of things, just considerations of building AI
것을 보기 위해 AI를 구축할 때 고려해야 할 여러
to see what humans don't see.
가지를 공유했습니다.
Sometimes we're pushing AI like fine grained recognition
때로는 새의 미세한 구분 같은 인간 능력을
of birds to go beyond human ability.
넘어서는 AI를 개발하기도 합니다.
Those are superhuman ability.
그것은 초인적인 능력입니다.
Sometimes we know humans are not good.
때로는 인간이 잘하지 못하는 점을 알고 있습니다.
We have bias or we have attention issues.
우리는 편향이 있거나 주의 집중에 문제가 있죠.
And then we want to use AI to help us.
그래서 AI를 사용해 도움을 받고자 합니다.
And then sometimes we genuinely have situations
그리고 때로는 정말 아무도 보지 않길 원하는
we don't want anyone to see.
상황이 있습니다.
And then how do you use AI to continue
그럴 때 AI를 어떻게 활용해 프라이버시를
to help without violating those privacy concerns?
침해하지 않으면서 계속 도움을 줄 수 있을까요?
So you can see that AI is a very interesting, powerful tool.
그래서 AI가 매우 흥미롭고 강력한 도구라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
It can both help but amplify us.
AI는 우리를 도울 수도 있고, 우리를 증폭시킬 수도 있습니다.
And if we have bias, if we have issues, AI can amplify us too.
그리고 만약 우리가 편견이나 문제가 있다면, AI도 그것을 증폭시킬 수 있습니다.
So when we build AI, it is so important
그래서 AI를 만들 때는 기술적인
not only to take that technology perspective, but also
관점뿐만 아니라 인간적인 관점도 매우 중요하며,
to take the human perspective, to commit
예측을 연구하고 AI가
to study forecasts and guide the AI to understand
인간에 미치는 영향을 이해하며 인간의 가치를
its human impact and respect human values.
존중하도록 이끄는 데 전념해야 합니다.
So that's the second take home message.
이것이 두 번째 핵심 메시지입니다.
And again, a number of collaborators and students
그리고 다시 말해, 여러 협력자들과
participated in this work.
학생들이 이 작업에 참여했습니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
Now, let's talk about building AI
이제 AI를 만들어서 인간이 보고 싶어 하는 것을
to see what humans want to see.
보게 하는 것에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
And in fact, we're going to go beyond seeing.
사실 우리는 보는 것을 넘어서서,
We're going to connect seeing and doing together.
보는 것과 행동하는 것을 연결할 것입니다.
So if you think about today's societal anxiety about AI,
오늘날 AI에 대한 사회적 불안 중
one of the biggest anxiety is labor.
하나는 노동 문제입니다.
A lot of headline news will say, labor is under threat.
많은 헤드라인 뉴스가 노동이 위협받고 있다고 말하죠.
Robots taking over jobs.
로봇이 일자리를 빼앗는다는 이야기입니다.
The truth is, the picture is complex.
하지만 진실은 상황이 복잡하다는 겁니다.
Denying job change is wrong.
일자리 변화 자체를 부정하는 것은 잘못된 것입니다.
Every technological shift in human history
인류 역사에서 모든 기술적 변화는 노동
has caused labor market change, and some of them
시장 변화를 일으켰고, 그중 일부는 매우
are very painful.
고통스러웠습니다.
Some of them can lead to even civil wars and wars.
그 중 일부는 심지어 내전과 전쟁으로까지 이어질 수 있습니다.
But also, that change sometimes is inevitable.
하지만 또한, 그 변화는 때때로 불가피합니다.
And a tiny digression.
잠깐 딴 얘기를 하자면요.
A lot of the labor threat rhetoric
우리가 듣고 있는 노동 위협 담론의
that we have been hearing, think about physical labors.
대부분은 육체 노동을 생각하게 합니다.
But today, in the past two years,
하지만 오늘날, 지난
if you look at GenAI's impact is white collar jobs
2년간 GenAI의 영향은 특히 소프트웨어
that are drastically being impacted,
엔지니어링과 사무실 내 분석
especially software engineering and analytical work in offices.
업무 같은 화이트칼라 직업에 급격한 영향을 미치고 있습니다.
So there's just definitely a labor change.
그래서 분명히 노동 변화가 일어나고 있습니다.
But in the meantime, we also need
하지만 그 사이에, AI가
to recognize that AI I also can be helpful.
도움이 될 수도 있다는 점도 인식해야 합니다.
We actually fundamentally have human labor shortages
실제로 우리는 많은 상황에서 근본적으로 인력
in many situations, especially in elderly care, as well as
부족을 겪고 있습니다, 특히 노인 돌봄과 건강
health.
분야에서요.
First of all, as modern medicine improves,
우선, 현대 의학이 발전하면서 인간의
human life expectancy increases.
기대 수명이 늘어나고 있습니다.
And that is inevitably pushes a society towards longer living.
그리고 그것은 필연적으로 사회를 더 오래 사는 방향으로 밀어갑니다.
And that's a good thing.
그것은 좋은 일입니다.
But in the meantime, we have shortages of laborers.
하지만 그 사이에 노동자 부족 문제가 있습니다.
Young people need to work.
젊은 사람들이 일해야 합니다.
That's how to make this society vibrant.
그것이 이 사회를 활기차게 만드는 방법입니다.
Economy vibrant.
경제를 활기차게 만드는 거죠.
But who is taking care of our elderlies?
그런데 누가 우리 노인들을 돌보고 있습니까?
Who are taking care of our chronically ill?
만성 질환자를 돌보는 사람들은 누구일까요?
Even in America's hospitals, we have such a attrition
미국 병원에서도 특히 간호사를 중심으로
of health care workers, especially nurses,
의료 인력이 너무 많이 줄어들어
that we don't have enough hands, ears, eyes to help our patients.
환자를 도울 손과 귀, 눈이 부족한 상황입니다.
So instead of thinking about this word replace,
그래서 이 '대체(replace)'라는 단어를 생각하기보다는
we actually can think about AI augmenting.
AI가 보조(augment)하는 것으로 생각할 수 있습니다.
And you got a glimpse of that in my surgery room example.
제 수술실 예시에서 그 모습을 조금 보셨죠.
Indeed, in health, there's so many spaces in health
실제로 건강 분야에는 눈이 부족한
that we don't have enough pairs of eyes.
공간이 너무 많습니다.
And that's what I call the dark spaces of health.
저는 이를 건강의 어두운 공간(dark spaces)이라고 부릅니다.
From surgery room to patient room to pharmaceutical to homes
수술실에서부터 병실, 제약, 가정 등 다양한 곳이
and so on.
포함됩니다.
So how do we make AI help?
그렇다면 AI가 어떻게 도움을 줄 수 있을까요?
And this is something that Ihsan has been
이 부분은 Ihsan이 많은
leading a ton of this work.
연구를 이끌고 있습니다.
Also with zing is that we have been looking
또한 zing과 함께 우리는
at this problem of ambient intelligence for health,
스마트 센서와 머신러닝
where we combine smart sensors with machine learning algorithms
알고리즘을 결합해 건강 환경에서 중요한
to glean health critical insights from these situations
통찰을 얻고, 환자나 가족, 의사에게 적시에 알림을
in health set up so that we can alert the patients or family
주는 'ambient intelligence'
members or doctors in time to help patients.
문제를 연구해왔습니다.
And again, the fuller paper is in this particular paper
더 자세한 내용은 몇 년 전에 발표한
we published a couple of years ago.
논문에 있습니다.
Let me just give you a couple of examples.
몇 가지 예를 들어드리겠습니다.
One example is this hand hygiene project, which actually
첫 번째 예는 코로나 이전부터
started way before COVID.
시작된 손 위생 프로젝트입니다.
And hand hygiene turns out to be really important for keeping
손 위생은 병원 감염을 낮추는
hospital infection low.
데 정말 중요합니다.
Hospital acquired infection is actually
병원 내 감염은 미국 병원에서
one of the leading causes of American patients
환자 사망의 주요
fatality in our hospitals.
원인 중 하나입니다.
It kills three times more people per year than car accidents
연간 교통사고 사망자 수보다 세 배나 더 많은
nationwide, and it is really hard to control.
사람을 죽이며, 통제가 매우 어렵습니다.
Most of these germs are passed from patient room
대부분의 세균은 환자 방에서 환자 방으로
to patient room.
전파됩니다.
And then they just brew together.
그리고 나서 함께 증식하는 거죠.
So what do we do?
그럼 우리는 무엇을 해야 할까요?
The hospitals try to use human auditors,
병원에서는 인간 감사관을 사용하려고 하지만,
but we just talked about, we don't even have enough nurses,
방금 말했듯이 간호사도 충분하지 않은데
let alone hiring auditors.
감사관을 고용하는 것은 더 어렵습니다.
And also you cannot hire enough of them.
그리고 충분히 많이 고용할 수도 없습니다.
There are human fatigue.
사람은 피로를 느끼기 때문입니다.
We just talk about human attention problem.
우리는 인간의 주의력 문제에 대해 이야기한 겁니다.
So this is not a pretty prohibitive solution.
그래서 이것은 그다지 효과적인 해결책이 아닙니다.
There were some technological solutions like RFID,
RFID 같은 기술적 해결책도 있었습니다, 배지를
put the badge.
부착하는 거죠.
If the badge or the person wearing the badge
배지나 배지를 착용한
is close to the sink or the hand hygiene hand sanitizer
사람이 싱크대나 손 위생용 손 소독기 근처에 있으면, 그
dispenser, it gives you the hint that the person,
사람이, 보통 의사나 간호사가
or most likely the doctor or the nurses is washing their hands.
손을 씻고 있다는 신호를 줍니다.
But that's very nonspecific.
하지만 그건 매우 비특이적입니다.
You cannot guarantee.
보장할 수 없습니다.
And the hospital rooms are pretty small,
병실은 꽤 작고 복도도 좁아서,
corridors are small, and just standing next to something
무언가 옆에 서 있다고 해서 손을 씻고 있다는
doesn't mean you're doing it.
뜻은 아닙니다.
So a few years ago, we did this project
몇 년 전, 우리는 프라이버시를
where we put smart sensors that protects privacy
보호하기 위해 깊이 정보만 수집하는 스마트 센서를
by just only gleaning depth information like the blue screen
설치하는 프로젝트를 했습니다, 저 파란
or the blue video there.
화면이나 파란 영상처럼요.
And then we use computer vision algorithm to classify actions.
그리고 컴퓨터 비전 알고리즘을 사용해 행동을 분류했습니다.
Is the person washing hand or not washing hand?
그 사람이 손을 씻고 있는지 아닌지 말이죠.
And the result is that if you compare ground truth
결과적으로, 알고리즘 출력과
with the algorithm output versus human outputs or human detection
인간의 결과를 실제 정답과 비교해 보면, 알고리즘이 훨씬 더
results, you can see algorithm is so much better and more
우수하고 일관성이 있다는
consistent than humans.
것을 알 수 있습니다.
You have to almost show the same video to four humans
거의 AI만큼 좋은 결과를 얻으려면 거의 같은 영상을 네
to get almost as good as AI, and this is just not plausible.
명의 사람에게 보여줘야 하는데, 이는 현실적으로 불가능합니다.
If it's one person, you can see how sparse the detection is,
한 사람만 보면 탐지가 얼마나 드문지 알 수 있고, 이는
and that's not good.
좋지 않습니다.
So this is one application.
이것이 하나의 응용 사례입니다.
Another application we worked on is his ICUs.
우리가 작업한 또 다른 응용 분야는 ICU입니다.
ICU is where patients fight life and death.
ICU는 환자들이 생사를 다투는 곳입니다.
ICU is also where 1% of US GDP is spent.
ICU는 미국 GDP의 1%가 지출되는 곳이기도 합니다.
So making ICU as effective as safely as possible
그래서 ICU를 최대한 안전하고 효과적으로 만드는 것이
is a top priority.
최우선 과제입니다.
One of the goals or the goal of ICU
ICU의 목표 중 하나는 환자들을
is to get our patients safely out of ICU
안전하게 ICU에서 퇴원시켜 단계별
and go into step down units or even go home.
병동이나 집으로 보내는 것입니다.
So one of the most important thing people have learned in ICU
그래서 ICU에서 사람들이 가장 중요하게 배운 것 중 하나는
is to help patients to move.
환자들이 움직일 수 있도록 돕는 것입니다.
Proper movement, which we call mobilization,
우리가 동원(mobilization)이라고 부르는 적절한
is actually important for recovery.
움직임은 회복에 실제로 중요합니다.
But this is a very dicey situation.
하지만 이것은 매우 까다로운 상황입니다.
You have to get nurses to help.
간호사들의 도움이 필요합니다.
Doctors have to give orders, and you have to move properly,
의사들은 명령을 내려야 하고, 환자는 적절하게
and it has to be in different time, like designated time.
움직여야 하며, 지정된 시간에 해야 합니다.
And you have to assess the movement
그리고 움직임을 평가해야 하는데, 이
and all this is not easy, right?
모든 것이 쉽지 않습니다, 그렇죠?
So we collaborated with Stanford as well as Utah's Intermountain
그래서 우리는 Stanford와 Utah의 Intermountain
Hospital to put these smart sensors in ICU units
병원과 협력하여 ICU에 스마트 센서를
and help doctors to monitor patient movement,
설치하고 의사들이 환자의 움직임, 특히 침대에서 일어나기, 침대에 눕기,
in this particular case, four different kind of movements,
의자에서 일어나기, 의자에 앉기 등 네
getting out of bed, getting in bed, getting out of chair,
가지 움직임을 모니터링할 수 있도록
getting in chair.
도왔습니다.
These things are so important for ICU patients.
이것들은 ICU 환자들에게 매우 중요합니다.
I know that for us it's a no brainer,
우리에게는 당연한 일이지만,
but this really is critical.
정말로 중요한 문제입니다.
And you can see that I can help to do the kind of detection
그리고 제가 도울 수 있는 것은 의사들에게 매우
and prediction that is so helpful for doctors, especially
도움이 되는 감지와 예측을 하는 것입니다, 특히
when there's a labor shortage.
인력 부족 상황에서요.
Last, but not the least example is aging in place.
마지막이지만 결코 덜 중요하지 않은 예는 'aging in place'입니다.
And this is just so important for many, many reasons.
이것은 여러 가지 이유로 매우 중요합니다.
People are seniors, want to live at home independently
노인분들은 집에서 독립적이고 건강하게 살고
and healthily.
싶어 하십니다.
And I remember during the beginning of COVID
COVID 초기에 노인층에서
when we had so much fatality among the aging seniors.
많은 사망자가 발생했을 때가 기억납니다.
A lot has to do with hospital overrun and overtaxed hospital
병원이 과부하되고 과도하게 부담을 받는 것과 관련이 많아서,
system, so putting and keeping seniors safe and well
노인분들을 집에서 안전하고 건강하게 지키는
in their homes is really critical.
것이 정말 중요합니다.
And using smart sensors, we can help
스마트 센서를 사용하면 감염을 조기에 감지하는
early detection of infection, especially
데 도움이 될 수 있습니다,
using thermal cameras or mobility,
특히 열화상 카메라나 이동성 감지, ICU에서
we just talked about in ICU, similar here
방금 이야기한 것과 비슷하게요,
or understanding sleep patterns or understanding
또는 수면 패턴이나 식습관을
dietary patterns.
이해하는 데도요.
All these are realms of possibilities
이 모든 것이 AI와 스마트
by AI and smart sensors.
센서가 가능한 영역입니다.
And then last but not least, what if there's still
그리고 마지막으로, 스마트 센서가 있어도 인력
labor shortage after smart sensors.
부족이 계속된다면 어떻게 할까요?
The thing about smart sensors is that they are information
스마트 센서는 정보를 수집하는
gathering system, but they cannot go there and help to turn
시스템이지만, 환자를 돌보거나
a patient or bring water and medicine pills to the elderly.
물이나 약을 가져다 줄 수는 없습니다.
So this brings us to the last technical topic, which is
그래서 마지막 기술 주제는
embodied AI, or we would call--
'embodied AI'인데,
large part of embodied AI is robotics.
여기서 큰 부분은 로보틱스입니다.
And this is where I find it extremely exciting
이 부분이 매우 흥미로운데, 인지와
because it closes the loop between perception and action.
행동 사이의 연결고리를 완성하기 때문입니다.
And if you think about the Cambrian explosion of evolution,
진화의 캄브리아기 폭발을 생각해 보면, 눈이 생기면서
when there's an onset of eyes animals start to move.
동물들이 움직이기 시작했습니다.
So the area of robotics is where we
로보틱스 분야는 보는 것과 행동하는 것을 연결하는
can close the loop between seeing and doing.
고리를 완성할 수 있는 곳입니다.
But it's not easy, right?
하지만 쉽지 않죠?
Robots, as much as we're very excited by them, still
로봇은 우리가 매우 흥분하는 만큼, 여전히
are very, very slow.
매우, 매우 느립니다.
They are very, very clumsy.
로봇은 매우, 매우 서툴러요.
It's very hard for them to adapt to a generalizable situation.
일반화 가능한 상황에 적응하는 것이 매우 어렵습니다.
And in today's robotic research, we as a field
오늘날 로봇 연구 분야에서 우리는 많은
have made a ton of progress, and Stanford is definitely
진전을 이루었고, 스탠포드는 확실히 로봇 학습의
one of the centers of robotic learning.
중심지 중 하나입니다.
But still, most of these work are constrained in their setup,
하지만 여전히 대부분의 연구는 제한된 환경에서
our short horizon tasks pick and place,
이루어지고 있고, 단기
and it has anecdotal setup and lack of clinical--
과제인 집기와 놓기 작업에 국한되어 있으며, 일화적인 설정과 표준
sorry, lack of standard benchmark.
벤치마크의 부족이 있습니다.
So let me just share with you a couple of work in our lab.
그래서 우리 연구실의 몇 가지 연구를 공유하겠습니다.
One work is, a few years ago, we're
몇 년 전 한 연구는 로봇을 야생
looking at how to bring robots to the wild.
환경으로 데려가는 방법을 살펴보았습니다.
If we have to predesignate the set of tasks, it's unsatisfying.
만약 우리가 미리 작업 세트를 지정해야 한다면, 만족스럽지 않습니다.
On the other hand, if you look at today's LLM,
반면에 오늘날의 LLM은 완전히
it's totally in the wild.
야생 환경에 있습니다.
You can talk about anything.
무엇이든 이야기할 수 있죠.
So my student want to learn and a few students
그래서 제 학생 몇 명이 이 간극을
want to close this gap.
메우고 싶어 했습니다.
So this idea is that how do we give
이 아이디어는 로봇에게 열린 지시를 어떻게
an open instruction to a robot, any instruction
주느냐, 즉 닫힌 세계에서 모든 것을
without pretraining everything in a closed world and the robot
사전 학습하지 않고도 로봇이 어떤 작업을 수행할 수 있게 하는
can do some tasks?
방법입니다.
So let's say your training set is open a door like that.
예를 들어, 훈련 세트가 '문을 열어라'라고 한다면,
In the wild, you have doors like that.
야생에는 그런 문들이 있습니다.
So how do you make some progress in that problem?
그 문제에서 어떻게 진전을 이룰 수 있을까요?
So the goal is, in the wild, generalization.
그래서 목표는 실제 환경에서의 일반화입니다.
And here is a result or overall algorithm.
여기 결과 또는 전체 알고리즘이 있습니다.
I don't know if this is so glitchy, but whatever.
이게 그렇게 오류가 많은지는 모르겠지만, 어쨌든요.
What you're saying is we want to tell this robot
말씀하신 것은 이 로봇 팔에게 꽃을
arm to open a drawer by planning a motion path that avoids
쓰러뜨리지 않도록 움직임 경로를 계획해서 서랍을 열라고
knocking down that flower.
하는 거죠.
And all these instructions were not pretrained.
그리고 이 모든 명령은 사전 학습된 것이 아닙니다.
So what we do is actually we borrow the latest advances
그래서 우리는 최신 LLM과 시각 언어
in LLM as well as in visual language model.
모델의 발전을 차용합니다.
And the idea is that we use LLM and VLM to give us
아이디어는 LLM과 VLM을 사용해 명령 세트를 만드는
an instruction set.
것입니다.
And then we use visual language model
그리고 시각 언어 모델을 사용해
to help us to recognize or understand the environment.
환경을 인식하거나 이해하는 데 도움을 받습니다.
And then we turn that into a motion planning map
그다음에 그걸 모션 플래닝 맵으로 바꿔서
so that the robotic arm can execute.
로봇 팔이 실행할 수 있게 합니다.
And because we're using LLMs as well as VLMs,
그리고 저희가 LLM과 VLM을 함께 사용하기
we get rid of the problem of training robot in a closed world
때문에, 로봇을 닫힌 세계에서 훈련하는 문제를 없애고 더 일반화되거나
and bring them to a more generalizable or in the wild.
실제 환경에서도 작동할 수 있게 합니다.
And the details is the instruction of open top drawer
자세한 내용은 '열린 상단 서랍'이라는 명령이
comes in.
들어오는 겁니다.
LLM turns this into like literally codes.
LLM이 이걸 문자 그대로 코드로 변환합니다.
And then because of these instructions
그리고 '서랍'이나 '손잡이'
like draw or handle, we send this information to a VLM model.
같은 명령 때문에 이 정보를 VLM 모델에 보냅니다.
And that model detects draw and handle in the scene.
그 모델이 장면에서 서랍과 손잡이를 감지합니다.
And then because of that, it updates its information,
그 결과 정보를 업데이트하고, 모션
and then it updates a motion map.
맵도 갱신합니다.
This is presented by a heat map to show you
이것은 히트맵으로 표현되어 로봇 팔이
where the robot arm should focus,
어디에 집중해야 하는지, 어디에
where it should not focus, and with that, then you
집중하지 말아야 하는지를 보여줍니다. 그리고 나서
give it another instruction, but watch out for the vase.
또 다른 명령을 주는데, 꽃병을 조심하라는 겁니다.
Again, it goes through the same thing with LLM, writes the code
다시 말해, LLM을 통해 같은 과정을
or generate the code, send it through a VLM model.
거쳐 코드를 작성하거나 생성하고, VLM 모델에 전달합니다.
VLM model detects the object and then updates the motion planning
VLM 모델이 객체를 감지한 후 모션 플래닝 맵을
map.
업데이트합니다.
In this case, it's the negative, not the positive,
이 경우에는 피해야 하므로 긍정이
because you want to avoid that.
아니라 부정입니다.
And then combining with the previous map,
그리고 이전 맵과 결합하면 어디를 피하고
you get a heat map of knowing where to avoid and where to go.
어디로 가야 하는지 알 수 있는 히트맵을 얻습니다.
And eventually what we do is we do this for the motion planning
결국 우리가 하는 것은 모션 플래닝 맵에 대해 이 작업을 수행하는
map.
겁니다.
We do it for rotation to gripper, velocity,
회전, 그리퍼, 속도에 대해서도
and then this is the result. Actually,
하고, 이것이 결과입니다. 사실, 이걸
let me just show you this.
보여드리겠습니다.
This is the actual result of the robot.
이것이 로봇의 실제 결과입니다.
And then we do this for many different tasks, right?
그리고 여러 다른 작업에 대해서도 이렇게 합니다, 맞죠?
We can do it for articulated object manipulation.
관절형 객체 조작에도 할 수 있습니다.
We can do it--
여기 다양한
here just many different examples.
예시들이 있습니다.
Napkins or sweeping the floor.
냅킨이나 바닥 쓸기 같은 거죠.
What is this?
이게 뭐죠?
Getting toast, setting up table, and also
토스트를 꺼내고, 테이블을 세팅하고, 온라인
dealing with online disturbances and so on.
방해 요소도 처리하는 겁니다.
So this is one work.
이게 한 가지 연구입니다.
Another work I want to just show you quickly
또 다른 연구를 간단히 보여드리자면,
is that overall robotics research is still lacking
전반적인 로봇 연구는 아직 좋은 벤치마크가 부족합니다.
good benchmark, and while we're still experimenting in the labs,
실험실에서는 계속 실험하지만, 실제 세계는 훨씬 더
we know real world is so much more complex, so much more
복잡하고 불확실하며, 변동성이 크고,
uncertain, have large variability,
상호작용적이고 사회적이며,
is so interactive and social, and it
다중 작업이 많다는
has a lot of multitasking task.
걸 알고 있습니다.
And then we know that both natural language and computer
자연어와 컴퓨터 비전 분야가 훈련과
vision has benefited a lot from setting up important large scale
벤치마크를 위한 중요한 대규모 데이터셋 구축으로 많은
data sets for both training and benchmark.
혜택을 본 것도 알고 있습니다.
So in our lab, we have been working on this project that
그래서 저희 연구실에서는 생태학적
is towards an building an ecological robotic learning
로봇 학습 환경을 구축하고, 연구자들이 크고 다양한
environment and try to encourage researchers
활동 집합에 대해 벤치마크할 수 있도록
to benchmark against a large and diverse set of activities.
장려하는 프로젝트를 진행하고 있습니다.
And that's the behavior of benchmark,
이것이 바로 일상 가사
which is benchmark for everyday household
활동을 위한 가상 상호작용
activities in virtual interactive and ecological
생태 환경에서의 행동
environments.
벤치마크입니다.
Now, here's a question because this lecture has a lot
이 강의가 인간의 가치와 관련이 많기
to do with human values is, who is to say
때문에 질문이 하나 있습니다. 로봇이 어떤 작업을
which tasks robots should do?
해야 하는지는 누가 결정하나요?
I know that every graduate students
로봇 연구를 하는 대학원생들은
who are working on robotics just want two tasks.
보통 두 가지 작업만 원합니다.
One is laundry, the other one is dishwasher.
하나는 세탁, 다른 하나는 식기세척기입니다.
That's great, but moving beyond grad school, what are the tasks
좋습니다만, 대학원 이후에는 로봇에게 어떤 작업을
we should get robots to do for us?
시켜야 할까요?
So instead of us coming up with this task list,
그래서 우리가 작업 목록을 만드는 대신, 인간 중심
we actually did a human-centered survey to ask robots--
설문조사를 통해 사람들에게 물어봤습니다—아, 죄송합니다, 로봇에게가
or sorry to ask humans--
아니라
[LAUGHTER]
사람들에게요—[웃음]—로봇이
--that what would you like robots to help you?
어떤 도움을 주길 원하는지요?
Let me test this.
테스트해 보겠습니다.
Would you like a robot to help you to clean the kitchen floor?
로봇이 주방 바닥 청소를 도와주길 원하시나요?
Say yes or no.
예 아니오로 대답하세요.
OK, good.
좋습니다.
Normal people would say yes.
보통 사람들은 예라고 할 겁니다.
Shoveling snow?
눈 치우기?
OK.
좋습니다.
Folding laundry?
세탁물 개기?
Yes.
네.
OK, good.
좋습니다.
Cooking breakfast?
아침 준비 중이신가요?
No.
아니요.
Yes.
네.
See, we're getting mixture answers, right?
보시다시피, 답변이 섞여 나오고 있죠?
What about opening Christmas gift?
크리스마스 선물 열기는 어떤가요?
No.
아니요.
Exactly.
정확합니다.
People are different.
사람들은 다릅니다.
I actually think robot can do this pretty well,
사실 로봇이 이걸 꽤 잘할 수
but we don't want it.
있다고 생각하지만, 우리는 원하지 않습니다.
One of the tasks we ask is buying wedding rings.
우리가 요청하는 작업 중 하나는 결혼 반지 사기입니다.
Can you imagine that?
상상할 수 있나요?
So what we did is actually-- we want
그래서 우리가 한 것은, 인간의 선호를
to respect human preference.
존중하고자 했습니다.
So we took a bunch of government surveys
미국과 유럽 노동부의
from a labor office in the US and Europe and so on,
정부 설문조사를 모아서 수천
and put together thousands of everyday activity tasks.
개의 일상 활동 작업을 정리했습니다.
And then we went online to find people.
그리고 온라인에서 사람들을 찾았습니다.
We want to be as diverse as possible,
가능한 한 다양하게 하려고
but I think we have room to improve.
했지만, 개선할 여지가 있다고 생각합니다.
But we found 1,400 people.
하지만 1,400명을 찾았습니다.
And to answer these tasks and tell us
이 작업들에 답변하고 로봇이 도움을 주길 원하는
which tasks they want robots to help, and then we rank that.
작업을 알려주면, 그걸 순위 매겼습니다.
And you can see that just like grad students,
보시다시피 대학원생들처럼, 사람들은 청소,
people want robots to help with cleaning, a lot of cleaning,
특히 화장실 청소, 바닥 청소에 로봇이 도움을
toilet cleaning, floor cleaning, but people don't want robots
주길 원하지만, 스쿼시를 대신해주거나 결혼
to play squash for you, or to buy a wedding ring,
반지를 사주거나 아기 시리얼을 섞어주는
or to even mix baby cereals.
것은 원하지 않습니다.
There is a lot of tasks that matters
인간에게 감정적이거나
to us as humans, emotionally or socially or whatever.
사회적으로 중요한 작업들이 많습니다.
So our goal is first we have a principled way to decide which
그래서 우리의 목표는 먼저 원칙에 따라 로봇을 훈련시킬 1,000개의 작업을 결정하는
are the 1,000 tasks that we want to train robots for, and those
것입니다. 그 작업들은 인간이 도움을 받고
are the tasks that humans prefer to get help.
싶어 하는 작업들입니다.
And with that in mind, we have to actually build
그걸 염두에 두고, 실제로 가상 환경을
a virtual environments.
만들어야 했습니다.
So we scanned or acquired 3D scene from 50 different real
우리는 레스토랑, 아파트, 식료품점, 사무실 등 50가지
world environments from restaurants to apartments
실제 환경에서 3D
to grocery stores to offices and so on.
장면을 스캔하거나 획득했습니다.
And then we acquired, this number is actually outdated,
그리고 이 숫자는 업데이트 전이지만, 10,
we acquire more than 10,000 object assets,
000개 이상의 3D 객체 자산을
3D assets that has a lot of properties,
획득했으며, 관절성, 변형
whether it's articulation, deformability,
가능성 등 다양한 속성을
and all those properties.
포함하고 있습니다.
And then we have to build a simulation environment.
그리고 시뮬레이션 환경을 구축해야 했습니다.
A lot of people have built simulation environment.
많은 사람들이 시뮬레이션 환경을 만들었죠.
Let me just fast forward.
잠시 건너뛰겠습니다.
But our particular simulation environment
하지만 우리 시뮬레이션 환경은 NVIDIA의
was a collaboration with NVIDIA's Omniverse group.
Omniverse 그룹과 협력하여 만들었습니다.
And we were going for building a physically,
우리는 물리적, 지각적, 그리고
perceptually, and also interactively
상호작용적으로 고품질의 시뮬레이션
high-quality simulation environment, and this especially
환경을 구축하려 했고, 특히 열 투과성,
taking account, for example, physical effects
변형 가능성
like thermal transparency, deformability and so on.
같은 물리적 효과를 고려했습니다.
We also tested our behavior environment
또한 인간 사용자 연구를 통해 지각적
against other environments in terms of perceptual realism
현실성 면에서 우리 환경을 다른 환경과
from human user study.
비교 평가했습니다.
And here are some of the examples
여기 천이나 액체
of physical interaction, such as cloth or liquids and so on.
같은 물리적 상호작용 예시들이 있습니다.
So there's a lot of nuance that has gone into this work.
이 작업에는 많은 미묘한 부분들이 포함되어 있습니다.
And let me just fast forward, and these are some benchmarks
자, 제가 그냥 빨리 넘길게요. 이것들은 다른 연구들과
we did compared to other work.
비교한 벤치마크 결과입니다.
OK.
네.
Let me just fast forward.
제가 빨리 넘기겠습니다.
So this is an ongoing work actually in our lab,
이것은 사실 우리 연구실에서
and because of this, we are using behavior
진행 중인 작업인데, 행동을 이용해서 로봇
to help us to learn robotics, to help us,
학습을 돕고, 더 흥미로운
actually, to push us to gather more interesting data
데이터를 수집하며,
and also to use that for even cognitive studies.
심지어 인지 연구에도 활용하고 있습니다.
Let me just fast forward.
제가 빨리 넘기겠습니다.
One thing I want to share with you is that--
여러분께 공유하고 싶은 한 가지는,
let me just share these numbers, is today's algorithm still
오늘날의 알고리즘으로는 아직 행동 과제를 수행할
cannot do behavior tasks.
수 없다는 점입니다.
And of all these roles, the top role
이 모든 역할 중에서 가장 위에 있는 역할이 우리가
is what we wish robots can do.
로봇이 할 수 있기를 바라는 역할입니다.
Give them no privileged information.
특권 정보를 전혀 주지 않고,
They have to be dropped in an environment and do these tasks.
로봇을 환경에 바로 투입해서 이 과제들을 수행하게 하는 겁니다.
And we benchmarked three behavior tasks
우리는 오늘날의 로봇 알고리즘으로
using today's robotic algorithm.
세 가지 행동 과제를 벤치마킹했는데,
And the performance is just zero.
성능은 거의 0에 가깝습니다.
And once you start to give more privileged information
하지만 더 많은 특권 정보를 주거나, 마법
or make assumptions that make the task
같은 움직임이나
simpler, like magic motion or a perfect memory and all that,
완벽한 기억 같은 가정을 해서 과제를 단순화하면,
things start to get better.
성능이 점점 좋아집니다.
If you look at it, only look at the top row,
위쪽 행만 보시면, 오늘날 로봇들이 얼마나
you get pretty depressed by today's robots.
실망스러운지 알 수 있습니다.
But as a grad student, I hope you're
하지만 대학원생 여러분께는
inspired because that means we have a lot of room to grow.
영감을 드리고 싶습니다. 왜냐하면 성장할 여지가 많다는 뜻이니까요.
OK.
네.
These are just different papers from our lab.
이것들은 우리 연구실의 다른 논문들입니다.
I'm going to actually fast forward because I think
사실 이 부분은 충분히 이야기한
we've talked enough about this.
것 같아서, 빨리 넘기겠습니다.
Well, by the way, we're also doing digital twin of behavior
참고로, 우리는 디지털 환경과 실제 환경 모두에서
in the digital environment as well as
행동의 디지털 트윈을 만들고
in the real-world environment, and that's
있는데, 이것은 실제에서
a great way of testing real to sim transfer.
시뮬레이션으로의 전이를 테스트하는 좋은 방법입니다.
Again, this is an unsolved problem.
다시 말하지만, 이것은 아직 해결되지 않은 문제이고,
And there's a long way to go.
아직 갈 길이 멉니다.
And in this particular case, we're
특히 이 경우에는, 속도를
showing you that this robot, without speeding up,
높이지 않고도 이 로봇이 얼마나
you can see how slow it is.
느린지 볼 수 있습니다.
It's trying to clean up this room.
이 로봇은 방을 청소하려고 하고 있습니다.
OK.
네.
Hooray.
좋습니다.
This is actually some of the mistakes
이것은 이 로봇이 저지르는 몇
that this robot makes in--
가지 실수들입니다. 예를
for example, it cannot pick up the bottle,
들어, 병을 집지 못하거나, 아까는
or earlier it just went the wrong way and placed it
잘못된 방향으로 가서 잘못된 곳에 물건을
in the wrong place.
놓았습니다.
So there's still a lot of mistakes.
아직도 실수가 많습니다.
OK, let me fast forward.
네, 제가 빨리 넘기겠습니다.
We're actually we're also using this environment
우리는 이 환경을 시각 장애
to study visually impaired patients,
환자 연구에도 활용하고
and this is a great way of putting patients
있는데, 환자들을 안전한 환경에
in a safe environment to study.
두고 연구할 수 있는 좋은 방법입니다.
One last thing I want to show you is really super cool,
마지막으로 보여드리고 싶은 정말 멋진
and this is the last technical work I want to show
작업이 하나 있는데, 이것이 제가 보여드릴
is that we also now are collaborating with psychologists
마지막 기술 작업입니다. 우리는 심리학자와 의사들과 협력하여
and doctors to study how we can use brain waves to control
뇌파를 이용해 로봇을 제어하는 연구를 하고
robots.
있습니다.
So what you're seeing here is a demo
여기 보시는 것은
where a grad student, I think, is wearing this EEG cap,
대학원생이 EEG 캡을 쓰고,
and that just is sending instructions,
생각만으로 로봇 팔이
and the robotic arm is cooking a Japanese meal purely
일본 요리를 만드는
from thoughts.
시연입니다.
There's no invasive brain control.
침습적인 뇌 제어가 전혀 없습니다.
This is from electrical signals.
이것은 전기 신호에서 나온 것입니다.
What we have to do is to pretrain these thoughts.
우리가 해야 할 일은 이러한 생각들을 사전 학습하는 것입니다.
You have to pretrain the robotic arm with, say, lift or place
예를 들어, 로봇 팔을 들어 올리기, 놓기, 떨어뜨리기
or drop or whatever.
등으로 사전 학습해야 합니다.
And once you do that, this is an entire meal
그리고 그렇게 하면, 이 파동을 기반으로
cooked based on the wave.
한 완전한 식사가 완성됩니다.
This is really sci-fi.
이것은 정말 공상 과학 영화 같은 일입니다.
And this has happened last year.
그리고 이것은 작년에 일어났습니다.
So I'm pretty excited by where all this is going, combining
그래서 저는 시각, 인지, 로봇 공학을 결합하고 임상
vision and perception and robotics
환경에서 사람들을 돕는 이 모든
and also helping people in clinical settings.
방향에 대해 매우 기대하고 있습니다.
This is really the future of this
이것이 바로 중증
is helping severely paralyzed patients.
마비 환자들을 돕는 미래입니다.
OK, so behavior project is really
네, 그래서 행동 프로젝트는 사람들을 보조하는
aimed at augmenting people.
데 정말 초점을 맞추고 있습니다.
It's a large scale diverse benchmark.
이것은 대규모 다양성 벤치마크입니다.
And it has realistic and ecological physics
그리고 현실적이고 생태학적인 물리학과 인지를
and perception.
갖추고 있습니다.
And the last take home message is
마지막으로 전하고 싶은 메시지는, 우리는 단순히 AI가 무언가를
that we not only want to build AI to just do things or see
하거나 보게 만드는 것뿐만 아니라, 진정으로 사람들을 돕기
things, we really want to build it to help people.
위해 AI를 만들고 싶다는 것입니다.
AI being an augmentation tool or enhancing tool for humanity
AI가 인간을 대체하는 도구가 아니라 인간을 보조하고
is very important instead of a tool that replaces.
향상시키는 도구가 되는 것이 매우 중요합니다.